A Guide to the James Madison Memorabilia, 1796-1951
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
The James Madison Memorabilia 1796-1951
Special Collections, James Madison University
2099
This collection comprises one Hollinger and one Flat box, and contains miscellaneous items.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
All items were present in the metal screened area in the stacks called the Cage in September 1982, when the Special Collections program was initiated and Room 205 was designated for Special Collections. An undated, unsigned typescript inventory, referred to below as the original inventory, was also present. However, some items listed on the inventory were not present when the inventory was checked in Nov. 1982. The original inventory, and/or written materials accompanying the items, give provenance for some but not for all items. In early 1983 the Special Collections Librarian created an information sheet for each item and boxed the items as a collection. In 1994 the same Special Collections Librarian revised the organization of the collection and re-boxed it to be consistent with the standards developed for manuscript collections. The original inventory, the written materials that accompanied some items, and the information sheets created in 1983 (on which preservation history is noted) are filed in the control file in the Special Collections office.
Scope and Content Information
This collection comprises one Hollinger and one Flat box, 1796-1951, and contains miscellaneous items alleged to be related to James Madison. None of Madison's papers are included.
Contents List
- 1: Miscellaneous Materials
  - Letter from James Madison Sr. to Thomas Macon 1796 (Box-folder 1:1)
    Pasted onto cardboard sheet with envelope and clippings of proverbs. Fading ink at the top states: "This letter was written to my great grandfather by his father-in-law my great great grandfather. Corrie B.M. Hill."
  - Copies of John P. Madison's genealogical working papers, 35 pages, with 1951 cover letter to Dr. Gifford, Madison College, from Mildred Madison. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Five envelopes to S.P. Duke, Madison College President, with 4 cent Madison stamps canceled at 5 post offices relevant to Madison, on first day of issue, July 1, 1938, or shortly thereafter. (Box-folder 1:3)
- 2: Illustrative Materials
  - Postcard of girl and boy in early American dress. On back in fading pencil: "Dress of Sally Catlett Madison wife of Thomas Macon. When she died everybody on place went into mourning--negroes too." (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Two photographs of Corrie Hill of Culpepper, VA at her home. (1 tinted, 1 BandW, 8 x 10) (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Engraving of James Madison, by W.A. Wilmer from print by Edwin after original portrait by G.Stuart. Probably pulled from a book. (Box 1)
  - Engraving of D.T. Madison, by J.F.E. Prudhomme, drawn by J.Herring after J.Wood. (Box 1)
  - Engraving of James Madison seated at a desk, from original picture by Chappel, 10 + 1/2 x 8". (Box 1)
  - Engraving of James Madison by W. Wellstood from original by G. Stuart, 10 + 1/2 x 8". (Box 1)
  - Etching of James Madison by A. Rosenthal from G. Stuart., 10 + 1/2 x 8". (Box 1)
  - Engraving of Dolly Madison by J. Prudhomme, 5 + 3/4 x 7 + 3/4" (Box 1)
  - Portrait of James Madison by G. Stuart and H.B. Hall Jr., 5 + 3/4 x 7 + 3/4" (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Montpelier before house was remodeled, from C. Hill in 1940, BandW, frame in poor condition, 10 + 1/2 x 12 + 1/2". (Box 1)
  - Letter to F.H. Dillingham June 22, 1801. (Box-folder 1:5)
- 3: Documents signed by James Madison
  - Letter of Commission, 1 p., Joseph Kean to second Lieut., June 1, 1810. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:1)
  - Letter from Robert Brent, Paymaster of U.S. Army, to Pres. James Madison, Aug. 15, 1810. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:1)
  - Check for $200, Aug. 4, 1813, to A.B. or bearer. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:1)
  - Letter of Commission, 1 p., Joseph Kean to capt., Feb. 1, 1815. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:1)
  - Letter of Commission, 1 p., A. McFarland to 3rd lieut., May 1,1815. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:1)
  - Letters Patent, 2 pages, parchment. Granted to Samuel Gragg 1808 for elastic chair. T. Jefferson, Pres., and J. Madison, Sec'y of State. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:2)
- 4: Newspapers
  - July 21, 1812 Liberty Hall, v. 8, no. 400 (contains text of an act approved by J. Madison) (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
  - Dec. 3, 1836 National Intelligencer, v. 37, no. 5382, with eulogy on J. Madison by J.Q. Adams. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
- 5: Artifacts
  - Lancet with short blade at one end and red box with green plush lining. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:1)
  - Indian Peace Medal presented by Pres. James Madison in 1809 to an Indian chief for his efforts toward peace; 76 mm., silver. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
  - Medal with bust in honor of James Madison. 35 mm, uncirc., bronze. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
  - Pistol, 13 1/2". (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
  - Pocket knife, pearl-handled, most of 14 blades broken or missing. The initial M is scratched on both sides of handle. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
  - Saltcellar, broken on one side, chipped in several places. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
  - Scales, box, and four weights. Box in poor repair. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)
  - Spyglass, inscribed on inside tube: W. Harris Holborn London Day or Night. Loose lens. (Box-folder FLAT Box 1:3)